RG 079:022, Forestry Department
Connecticut State Library
Forestry Department records
circa 1901-2004
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Forestry Dept
28.25 cubic feet
In 1921 the General Assembly reorganized the state forest administration. The State Park Commission became the State Park and Forest Commission and had authority to appoint the state forester, separating that office from the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station.
RG079_022
T003192 and 2013-010
Historical Note
Connecticut was the first New England state to enact legislation regarding state forests. In 1901 the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station at New Haven employed a forester to investigate forestry problems and advise land owners. Shortly after, the General Assembly passed a law making the Experiment Station forester ex-officio state forester. Provision was also made for the purchase of land for state forests largely for experimental and demonstration purposes. The first purchase was a tract of 70 acres in the town of Portland acquired in 1903. In 1905 the state forester also became the state forest fire warden. Town fire wardens would be appointed by the selectmen of the various towns. In 1921 the General Assembly reorganized the state forest administration. The State Park Commission became the State Park and Forest Commission and had authority to appoint the state forester, separating that office from the Experiment Station.1 In 1971, the functions of the Forestry Department were incorporated into the new Department of Environmental Protection.
Endnotes
1Report of the State Park and Forest Commission to the Governor, For the Fiscal Term Ended June 30, 1922, Hartford, Conn., 1922; Austin F. Hawes, The State Forests of Connecticut and What They Are For, Hartford, Conn., 1934, 5.
Scope and Content
The photographs, circa 1908-1940, bulk 1920-1940 include meetings and gatherings of people; various state forests including Cockaponset, Mohawk, Meshomasic, Mattatuck and others; fire towers and fire fighting equipment; lumbering; insects and diseases; educational; boy scout activities; buildings; plantations; and other miscellaneous subjects.
Accession 2013-010 is unprocessed and covers circa 1901-2004. Included is correspondence, fire warden bills, state forestry records, publications, and photographic slides.
Related Material
RG 079:016, Department of Environmental Protection: Natural Resources and Outdoor Recreation
RG 079:017, State Park and Forest Commission
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Forestry Dept; Connecticut. Dept. of Energy & Environmental Protection. Forestry Division
Subjects:
Connecticut. Dept. of Energy & Environmental Protection. Forestry Division -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut. Forestry Dept -- Records and correspondence; Forests and forestry -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Maps; Photographs; Reports; Slides (photographs)
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
Accession 2013-010 was transferred to the Connecticut State Library from the Department of Energy and Environmental Protection, Forestry Division on September 17, 2012.
Container List
- Photographs, circa 1908-1940, bulk 1920-1940; T003192; 1.25 cubic feet
  - People: Groups, meetings, gatherings, 21 photographs (Box 1)
  - Cockaponset State Forest, 34 photographs (Box 1)
  - Mohawk State Forest, 25 photographs (Box 1)
  - Meshomasic State Forest, 36 photographs (Box 1)
  - Mattatuck State Forest, 12 photographs (Box 1)
  - Other State Forests, 15 photographs (Box 1)
  - Connecticut State Parks, 15 photographs (Box 1)
  - Fire towers, 13 photographs (Box 1)
  - Fire fighting equipment, 13 photographs (Box 1)
  - Lumbering, 10 photographs (Box 1)
  - Diseases, Insects, 8 photographs (Box 1)
  - Educational - Tree contest, 11 photographs (Box 2)
  - Educational - Miscellaneous, 8 photographs (Box 2)
  - Boy Scout activities, 6 photographs (Box 2)
  - Buildings: Miscellaneous, 11 photographs (Box 2)
  - Signs, 8 photographs (Box 2)
  - Slides, charts: Connecticut forests, 12 photographs (Box 2)
  - Plantations (Box 2)
    - Private: Gold, Goodwin, Whittemore, 17 photographs (Box 2)
    - Private: Other, 21 photographs (Box 2)
    - Nepaug Reservoir, Rainbow Forest, 16 photographs (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 28 photographs (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Trees, 20 photographs (Box 2)
    - Rivers and ponds, 19 photographs (Box 2)
    - Recreation and camps, 9 photographs (Box 3)
    - Fires, storms, fire prevention, 12 photographs (Box 3)
    - Other states, 24 photographs (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 27 photographs (Box 3)
- Accession 2013-010, circa 1901-2004; 27 cubic feet
  This accession is unprocessed.
  The following is a preliminary inventory. The container list for boxes 18-26 was provided by DEEP, Forestry Division.
  - Correspondence, 1923-1939 (Box 1-2A)
    Box numbers are 1, 1A, 2, 2A
  - Fire warden bills, 1934-1935 (Box 1-1A)
  - Publications, 1913-1957, 1996 (Box 3)
  - State inventory, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Marketing Committee, marketing organizations, correspondence, 1938 (Box 3)
  - Marketing data, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Index to type map books, undated (Box 3)
  - Old record of surveys received, 1938-1943 (Box 3)
  - Blank forms, undated (Box 3)
  - Apple box manufacturing program, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Tunxis State Forest maps, undated (Box 3)
  - Purchase area reports, 1943-1945 (Box 3)
  - Obsolete forest areas on topo sheets, undated (Box 3)
  - Wood fuel, 1938-1943 (Box 3)
  - Forest fire fighters service instructor's manual, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous tables and charts, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1947 (Box 3)
  - Ranger's manual, undated (Box 3)
  - Inventory, 1945 (Box 3)
  - N supply, 1938-1943 (Box 3)
  - Danger station report, 1952 (Box 3)
  - United States Department of Agriculture publications, 1917-1981, bulk 1917-1940 (Box 4)
  - Scantic River State Park, circa 1981-1997 (Box 4)
  - Eastern District annual reports, 1931-1967 (Box 5)
  - Binder, 1936-1965 (Box 6)
    Contents: Conservation courses for C.C.C. Camps, 1936; short papers on landscaping in state forests, 1936-1937; ski trails, undated; control of exposed soil on road banks, undated; F forest aerial photo interpretation, 1965.
  - Maps, undated (Box 6)
    Contents: Housatonic, Mohawk, Tunxis, People's, Legion, Algonquin, Paugnet, Mepaug, Simsbury, Mattatuck, Naugatuck, Pootatuck.
  - Youth Conservation Corps photographic slides (Box 6)
  - Wood block photo templates, undated (Box 7)
  - State forest nursery records, circa 1942-2004, bulk 1973-2004
    Includes irrigation records, orchard records, market research, equipment manuals, office procedures, seedling trials, seed bed records.
    - Germination tests, 1957-2003 (Box 8)
    - Seedling planting and inventories, 1956-2000 (Box 8)
    - Equipment manuals (Box 9)
    - Seed bed record forms (blank) (Box 9)
    - Irrigation records, 1958-1987, 2001 (Box 10)
    - Market research study, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Seedling records, 1998-2001 (Box 10)
    - Arbor Day, 2003 (Box 10)
    - Field Days, 1971 (Box 11)
    - Information pamphlets, 1965-1976 (Box 11)
    - Connecticut laws relating to parks, forests & forestry, 1962 (Box 11)
    - Connecticut's open space program: a case study of party control of the legislature / by Gregory Curtis, 1963 (Box 11)
      M.A. Thesis, Trinity College
    - Connecticut's natural resources: a proposal for action, 1962 (Box 11)
    - GFA special forestry project, 1972 (Box 11)
    - Office procedures (Box 12)
    - Seedling trials, 1942-2004 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1902-1928 (Box 13)
  - Day book, 1901-1909 (Box 13)
  - Forest type map, topo-map, Natchaug State Forest, 1921 (Box 13)
  - Wooden Nutmeg, 1926-1941 (Box 13)
    Published by the Connecticut Department of Forestry
  - Miscellaneous records, 1901-1982 (Box 14)
    Includes inventories, maps, publications, reports. Also manuscripts related to forestry in Connecticut consisting of talks, copies of materials sent to the press, and related items, principally by Hawes, Tulley, Spring, 1901-1944, bulk 1920-1939.
  - Permanent file, 1948-1956 (Box 15)
    Contains various reports.
  - Town forests, 1941-1961 (Box 15)
  - Reports to commissions, 1945-1956, undated (Box 15)
  - Reports, annual, 1949-1967 (Box 15)
  - Manual outlines, annual report, ranger management plan, undated (Box 15)
  - Commission on Forests and Wildlife, 1932-1948 (Box 15)
  - Attorney General rulings, 1912-1969 (Box 15)
  - Burlington fire tower guest book, 1931-1944 (Box 15)
  - State Forester and State Forest Fire Warden in account with State of Connecticut, 1907-1910 (Box 15)
  - State Forester and State Forest Fire Warden in account with State of Connecticut, 1905-1910 (Box 15)
  - Publications, 1878, 1933-1947, 1902, 1970 (Box 16)
  - Governor's annual reports, 1977-1994 (Box 16)
  - Multiple use forestry in megalopolis: a case study of the evolution of forest policies and programs in Connecticut / by R. Douglas S. MacDonald, 1969 (Box 16)
    Ph.D. Diss., Yale University
  - State Park and Forest Commission, 1955-1962 (Box 16)
  - Forestry progress & notes for commission meetings, 1958-1970 (Box 16)
  - Pachaug Forest guest register, 1957-1979 (Box 16)
  - Permanent file, 1956-1967 (Box 16)
    Various papers on forestry
  - Correspondence, 1912-1940 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence - People's State Forest, 1922-1928 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence - Tunxis State Forest, 1923-1928 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence - American Legion, 1927-1928 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence - Mattatuck State Forest, 1925-1929 (Box 17)
    Formerly Naugatuck State Forest
  - People's State Forest, undated (Box 17)
    Contains a paper by Austin F. Hawes, State Forester and a plan of the track trail bridge, Beaver Brook, People's State Forest
  - Correspondence - Boy Scouts of America, 1926 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence - Mohawk State Forest, 1928-1929, 1946 (Box 17)
  - Housatonic State Forest cards, 1935-1936 (Box 17)
  - Mohawk State Forest cards, 1936 (Box 17)
  - Housatonic State Forest - Canaan Mountain Block - maps, 1938-1951 (Box 17)
  - Plans for Paugnut Forest headquarters, undated (Box 17)
  - Forest patrolmen manual, 1951 (Box 17)
  - State nursery records, circa 1951-1999
    - Pachaug Nursery operating manual (Box 18)
    - Evapotranspiration studies (Box 18)
    - Soil moisture tests (Box 18)
    - Cutting and cottonwoods (Box 18)
    - Air layering (Box 18)
    - Pitch pine (Box 18)
    - Pachaug Forest (Box 18)
    - Tree breeding (Box 18)
    - Selected tree records (Box 18)
    - Nursery records (Box 18)
    - Nematodes (Box 18)
    - Quarantine requirements (Box 18)
    - Inventory (seedbed) (Box 18)
    - Nurseries (other) (Box 18)
    - Mulch (Box 18)
    - Rodent control (Box 18)
    - Root pruning (Box 18)
    - Seed collection (Box 18)
    - Seed testing (Box 18)
    - Irrigation (Box 18)
    - Forest fertilization (Box 18)
    - American Indians in CT: past to present (Box 18)
    - Future forests: predictions (Box 18)
    - Forests: present supply (Box 18)
    - YFCP mail out (Box 18)
    - White oak info (Box 19)
    - Gypsy moth plots (Box 19)
    - Field related correspondence (Box 19)
    - Statistics / marketing trends (Box 19)
    - 0-5B marketing (Box 19)
    - 0-5B Forest products utilization (Box 19)
    - Forest products price (Box 19)
    - CT forest products report (Box 19)
    - Treatment to prevent splitting (Box 19)
    - Gluing, lamination, performance (Box 19)
    - Pulpwood (Box 19)
    - Billing for seedling stock (Box 19)
    - 1976 FY info (Box 19)
    - Seasonal position justification (Box 19)
    - Seed dealers (Box 19)
    - Shrub stock, 1968 (Box 19)
    - Nursery shipping (Box 19)
    - Seed supply sources (Box 19)
    - Out of state shipping correspondence (Box 19)
    - Out of state shipping 1978-1979 (Box 19)
    - Purchase orders (Box 19)
    - Credit order for 1979 (Box 19)
    - Vendors for 1978 (Box 19)
    - Credit due nursery (Box 19)
    - Nursery tours (Box 19)
    - I-4 cones and I-4 planting (Box 19)
    - Misc. requests (Box 19)
    - Materials (Box 19)
    - Hartford correspondence (Box 19)
    - CT nurserymen's (Box 19)
    - Northeastern Forest Nursery Association conference (Box 19)
    - Materials and supplies (Box 19)
    - Plans (Box 19)
    - Nursery practice (Box 19)
    - Sowing records, People's nursery (Box 19)
    - People's nursery binder (Box 19)
      Reports, inventory, records, prices
    - Plant propagation (Box 20)
    - Tree species folders (Box 20)
      - Chestnut (Box 20)
      - Black locust (Box 20)
      - Bristly locust (Box 20)
      - Tulip poplar (Box 20)
      - European alder (Box 20)
      - Crabapple (Box 20)
      - Fox grape (Box 20)
      - White pine (Box 20)
      - Black walnut (Box 20)
      - Red cedar (Box 20)
      - Black cherry (Box 20)
      - Doug fir (Box 20)
      - Butternut (Box 20)
      - Cottonwood (Box 20)
      - Autumn olive (Box 20)
      - High bush cranberry (Box 20)
      - Honey suckle (Box 20)
      - Hemlock (Box 20)
      - Scotch pine (Box 20)
      - White spruce (Box 20)
    - Propagation misc. hardwoods (Box 20)
    - Pines (Box 20)
    - 0-8 Research project (Box 20)
    - Direct seedling (Box 20)
      - Negative propagation (Box 20)
      - Seed propagation (Box 20)
      - Plant phys. (Box 20)
    - Black adler (Box 20)
    - Hybrid white pine (Box 20)
    - Pitch / loblolly (Box 20)
    - Larch (Box 20)
    - FPS orders, 1987-1988 (Box 20)
    - Tree planters notes, 1951-1959 (Box 20)
    - Tree planters notes, 1963-1969 (Box 20)
    - Tree planters notes, 1960-1969 (Box 21)
    - Tree planters notes, 1970-1981 (Box 21)
    - 2 modern gardening binders (Box 21)
    - For Mr. Brooks (Box 21)
    - Fisheries RIV records (Box 21)
    - Forest products utilization abstracts (Box 21)
    - State/private forestry, 1976-1979 (Box 21)
    - Memos, 1961-1964 (Box 21)
    - Forest patrolman manual, 1951 (Box 21)
    - Interdepartmental messages, 1970-1980 (Box 21)
    - Interdepartmental memos, 1965-1970 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 22)
    - Temp records, 1957-1969 (Box 22)
    - Seedlot numbers (x2) (Box 22)
    - Office and nursery equipment (Box 22)
    - Seedlot records (Box 22)
    - Notes - shipping - cone collection (Box 22)
    - Inventory; Areas 4, 5, 6, 7 (Hartford copy) (Box 22)
    - Pachaug nursery report (Box 23)
    - Forest seedlings - nursery (Box 23)
    - Inventory records (Box 23)
    - Pachaug nursery - originals study (Box 23)
    - Tree's forestry - elm chestnut disease (Box 23)
    - Pachaug nursery data (Box 23)
    - Final status report, common services program, FY 2001 (Box 23)
    - Nursery history (Box 23)
    - Statistics by year (Box 23)
    - CT nursery general (Box 23)
    - Chateau de Versailles (Box 23)
    - Correspondence to Hartford (Box 23)
    - Nursery status goals presentation (Box 23)
    - CT nursery - 5 year plan Cubanski/Smith (Box 23)
    - 1993 proposed budget (Box 23)
    - Budget expenditures (Box 23)
    - Jg 93/94 budget (Box 23)
    - J. Latarte analysis (Box 23)
    - Seed orchards / collection areas / prov. tests (Box 23)
    - Pine seed collection (Box 23)
    - MacDonald planting / white pine - Hopeville (Box 23)
    - White spruce pollinating (Box 23)
    - Goodwin - larch progeny tests (Box 23)
    - Market research study (Box 23)
    - Pitch / loblolly plantings (Box 23)
    - White pine provenance test 1981 Bibbons Pond (Box 23)
    - White pine - Waldo tract (Box 23)
    - Bristly locust seed orchard planting (Box 23)
    - Step rock, plantings (Box 23)
    - Rainbow forest plantings (Box 23)
    - Seed bank (Box 23)
    - N-5 Hadfields, N-5 Great Mountain Forest, N-5 Daniels lot (Box 23)
    - Nursery general budget info (Box 23)
    - Shipping and ordering info (Box 23)
    - nursery seedlings, 1987 (Box 23)
    - Nursery shipping summary, 1985 (Box 23)
    - Monthly accomplishment reports shipping summaries, 1990-1999 (Box 23)
    - Flexy disks (Box 23)
    - Annual reports, 1965-1972 (Box 24)
    - Natural stands record (Box 24)
    - Pachaug State Forest (Box 24)
      - Acre sheets (Box 24)
      - Summary cards (Box 24)
      - Records of cutting operations (Box 24)
      - Notes and plots (Box 24)
    - Seedling orders (Box 25)
    - Directives big-shade trees (Box 25)
    - Forestry meetings and minutes (Box 25)
    - State; tree improvement plans (Box 25)
    - Urban forestry (Box 25)
    - Land use planning (Box 25)
    - Water resources data - water year, 1981 (Box 25)
    - Orderings and receipts (Box 25)
    - Nursery annual reports (Box 25)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box 26)
    - General letters (Box 26)
    - Temperature records, 1970 (Box 26)
    - General correspondence In (Box 26)
    - CT Audubon Society correspondence (Box 26)
    - Quinnebaug Valley Engineers museum info (Box 26)
    - Correspondence from Hartford (Box 26)
    - Request for overnight vehicle (Box 26)
    - Website (Box 26)
    - Seedling brochures (originals), 1999-2000 (Box 26)
    - Info tech business plan (Box 26)
    - General correspondence out (Box 26)
    - Massachusetts conservation districts correspondence (Box 26)
    - Soil conservation correspondence (Box 26)
    - School yard wildlife habitat program (Box 26)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 26)
    - Nursery clerical manual (Box 26)
    - Jobs and hours spent on each (Box 26)
    - Region 7 cooperative nursery manual (Box 26)
    - Equipment (Box 26)
    - Olsen's book (Box 26)
    - Market research study (x3) (Box 26)
    - Market research study (special) (Box 26)
    - Federal reports (Box 26)
    - N.E. seed bank (Box 26)
    - Departmental memo's (Box 26)